so thank you everybody for uh coming
along to uh this week's magnet seminar
um we've got a little bit of a slightly different
seminar from our traditional uh uh purely science
talks this week so i'm really looking forward
to today's presentation um for those who haven't
um been to one of our seminars before uh we
typically will have a presentation that's
about 25 to 30 minutes long or so so we kindly ask
that you keep your microphones muted um so it's
not to interrupt speaker uh if you are having
problems with your connection uh we recommend
turning off um your camera and that can help to to
improve connection at the end of the seminar we'll
have time for us up 10 to 15 minutes um question
and discussion session um we'll invite you to unm
your microphones to ask your questions if you
don't want to to to use your microphone you type
a question into the chat and i will read it out
to to the presenters and at the very end of all
this we have time for a bit of a social catch-up
this is not recorded and this is just a chance for
us to all uh catch up and have a bit more of
a friendly discussion uh at the end of it all
so today i'm i'm really quite pleased to announce
that we have uh lewis braddock clark and susannah
as zakiepska i apologize if i've said that wrong
i'm from the royal academy of art in the hague and
today they're going to be presenting how to focus
uh paleomagnetic listening so i'll hand over to
the presenters awesome okay uh yeah
welcome everyone uh yeah we'd like to thank
vanderburn first of all and the whole magnetix
team for inviting us here this evening it's a
real special opportunity for us to also
have this type of context and everyone
here joining online so thanks for being here um
yeah as greg said already we are louis and susanna
we're both lecturers at the royal academy of art
in the hague and we work together also as a artist
duo in the hague so we run like a studio practice
here as researchers and creative practitioners
we survey the landscapes of geological anomalies
anthropogenic displacement and different types
of techno cultures we use the original and
experimental techniques to challenge and explore
the boundaries of also documentary filmmaking
in times of these accelerated geographies
and today we're going to share insights of our
recent field research on metroid islands which
is in the north western part of greenland and
the results of our scientific experiments done
in collaboration with the paleomagnetic
laboratory at the utrecht university
so our new project is out of focus it's a kind of
audio visual experience exploring climate change
mineral extraction paleomagnetism and
postcolonialism in north and greenland and we
look at this through the changes in geomagnetism
and digital storytelling so this presentation
will take you down the crimson cliffs past the
fjord of the dead and over the signal mountain
a harpoon of light cuts through the heavens
the night sky turns to fire
a sound of a thousand whales
woman dog havoc one tudor havoc ii and akbarik
smash into the sleepy landscape of inna minamin
as they hit the ice their memories melt away
the walking stones forget where they come from
willing to offer their spirits to a new ground
i touch the walking stones when they sleep
their cold shiny bodies breathe and pulse
these masses of metal appear to be very heavy
by their journey they speak of the stars the sky
the fire by their color dark knight and by
their density the cohesion of terrestrial things
their liveliness excites me to morph them
further i scupped uruz knives and harpoon heads
in salumbo a novel from 1862 gustav luber
poetically portrays quote the abaders stones
which had fallen from the moon whirling in slings
of silver thread unquote meteorites have inspired
generations of artists poets and filmmakers and
also scientists to dream about other worlds and
reflect on human positioning within the universe
around 10 000 years ago a meteor shower hit the
grounds of the present-day cape york peninsula
in northern greenland the fragments of walking
stones spread across the crimson cliffs past the
fjord of the dead and over the signal mountain
in out of focus our new project we explore the
unique ability of these iron meteorites to lock in
magnetic information as an iron meteoroid burns
through the earth's atmosphere it heats up above
its curie temperature this 570 degree celsius
hot spell rewrites the stones magnetic data to
match the earthly parameters and simultaneously
erasing the information about its cosmic origin
these special powers of storing erasing
and overwriting data gave iron meteorites
the nicknames of hard drives from space and this
geological anomaly of falling stars sparked a
technological advancement in the arctic the
people of northern greenland called inuit
mined valuable oars from the extraterrestrial
material using basil stones as hammers they
would chip off meteorite fragments to model their
devices with every cl every clang bang and dong
they would unknowingly cause stress magnetism
effect changing the properties of the mineral
and alongside this technological application the
cultural significance of meteorites flourished
in myths and drum songs inspired the inaugurate
he gave names to the walking stones who became
protagonists of these stories inspired by this
idea of breeding spirits into the meteorites
agna kitsok woman dog havoc 1 tura havik
2 and akparirik reappeared as non-human
characters in autofocus through a series of art
scientific experiments in the arctic and at the
magnetic laboratory in utrecht samples of capriate
meteorites are demagnetized and then magnetized to
measure the process of gathering and reshaping
the geomagnetic data in meteorites is as follows
so first we obtain the samples of kpr meteorites
um then second the local inuit um who are called
the arctic highlanders these hunters they take
these samples and heat them up to their curie
point with a simple blow torch third we measure
the local geomagnetic field and its anomalies with
a magnetometer and then we take the meteorite
samples to the earth simulation lab at utrecht
university where leonard pick prepares them to
be measured so yeah cuts them and processes them
and then at the paleomagnetic laboratory
in utrecht we measure the sample's
magnetic values using a spinner magnetometer
the experiment in the lab is done also
in collaboration with leonard
de groat and rosa de boer
and finally we demagnetize new samples off the
meteorite and re-magnetize them according to the
red values of the samples blowtorched in greenland
so yeah in short we take the samples that we
changed in greenland with the help of
local hunters to holland and based on the
measurings the measurements we change other
samples to have the same type of magnetism
yeah so what it means for
our narrative is that in this
process of rewriting the meteorites
magnetic histories we create new stories
okay now we're kind of like switching between
each other so now i'll just unmute myself
okay in the past the havahim look people of
great irons decapitated the women meteorite
and sledged its head away this act
maddened the weather demon tupalak
who pierced a crack through the ice
sheet swallowing the heavenly stone
the thieves narrowly escaped death but
learned that nature shelters its own deposits
today mining companies drill out cut off
and measure up mineral samples as a result
of climate change the deposits previously
hidden under the ice cap in greenland are now
revealed the prospects of acquiring new
land with quote the most interesting assets
and vast deposit potentials unquote inspire
new mining startups to dig and explore
prices of minerals shrink and expand like
the arctic ice the licenses for digging
become investments for global players who bet
in favor of the unfolding ecological catastrophe
in this landscape of speculation an
uncertain climate may liquefy into cash flow
the melting of ice only encourages the extractive
mechanism present in this landscape for centuries
parallel to danish colonization the
19th century north pole expeditions
such as those led by american robert perry
set out to find and retrieve mineral trophies
in this process the greenlandic meteorites
found their ways to museums in new york and
copenhagen so here you can kind of see these
photos which we've taken from archives which
show the metric being taken to copenhagen
and to new york and there are some really
incredible stories about this whole process
because it's an incredibly heavy object also
this relocation of heaven stones also aligned
with the displacement of the insulated people
who guided their cherished
resources to the western shorelines
parallel to the extraction of the anikitsukamitri
perry took a group of greenlanders to new york
the indigenous people were disgracefully displayed
as a living anthropological zoo at the american
museum of natural history a century later after
a series of evictions instigated by the colonial
powers forced migration is now prompted by new
mining adventures dredgers bulldozers earth
augers oil drums and diesel generators creep into
the settlements and their magic hunting grounds
and yet the traditional iniquit way of life is
not only threatened by mining during a cafe meet
on metroid island a cafe make is like a kind of
casual coffee and cake session the elder karnak
nielsen shared his thoughts about the dangers
of the erratic climate and so this is a quote
these animals polar bears and narwhals come and
go they are living together with the weather
one winter they are here and the next winter
they are not here the weather is very unstable
hunting nowadays is hard and tiring
especially for those who rely on it
the locals do not only depend on wildlife as
a source of food but also consider hunting
rituals as the breathing heart of their identity
climate instability disrupts the traditional way
of life of the inuit by leaving them to a tragic
choice between the life-threatening danger of
hunting on thin ice or the kind of distress of
employment in the postcolonial power structure
for the greenlandic society the live geology of
the land can either become a garden or a grave
the auctioning of mineral licenses contributes
to a level of political and economic independence
from denmark in this view greenland's natural
heritage shifts from common good to commodity
and by doing so the garden of metals would become
liberated from the post-colonial power but then
sliced open by foreign mineral extraction and
these types of dilemmas are kind of constantly
going on in this part of greenland which we
were kind of experiencing when we were there
okay then we switch again this is it
means breath unused many breaths hela a breath of
life the spirit of every living being is borrowed
from the sky and the air around them i am a
seal i inhale the frosty ghosts to guard me
underwater i seek out a beautiful harpoon head
in order to exhale my life without pain if the
design follows the rule of ritual and custom my
spirit will reside in the harpoon head for one
night after my death the indigenous cosmology
animates the landscape as a breathing system
according to the inuit the breaths meaning spirits
of all living beings are borrowed from gila
which stands for the weather climate
consciousness and mind and many other things
in the moment of death bodies return their breaths
back to the landscape this exchange of spirits
portrays nature as a network
of interconnected parts
in northern greenland the cycles of
life and death are experienced daily
at the edge of the sea ice at the breathing holes
on doc's ledges and in kayaks traditionally and
still to this day the inuit use iron harpoons
for hunting according to a myth recorded in 1929
by the greenlandic danish anthropologist knew the
rasmussen quote the soul of a seal resides in the
harpoon head for one night after the seal has been
killed unquote for the inner hit this hunting tool
is not a weapon but a device to facilitate the
passage of breaths from one body to another the
contemporary norwegian ethnographer hans christian
golov describes a harpoon to be a quote medium of
continuity between living beings unquote making
harpoon heads out of extraterrestrial metal the
inuit envisioned the capacity of iron meteorites
to lock in magnetic data inspired by the inuit
relationship with the landscape ruled by weather
demons staggering rocks and exchanges of breaths
our projects out of focus proposes a new
reading of the greenlandic tormented tundra
the indigenous idea of gila connecting all
living things finds its contemporary expression
in spectral data woven out of geomagnetic
waves our custom-made microphones geotools
we call them detect magnetic anomalies caused
by climate change and mineral displacement
each of our magnetometers consists of a three
axis flux gate sensor and an electronic circuit
the data output amplified by the shifting
geomagnetism is converted into a sonic
representation this allows for listening life
to the spectral tundra and by immersing in these
sounds we would like to challenge the colonial
extractive relationship with the arctic landscape
um yeah and additionally the fragments of
walking stones as the inuhit people call them
shipped out of greenland by colonists and
explorers will return to the arctic landscape
the restitution of mineral trophies is followed by
the procedure of inserting a new magnetic moment
into a meteorite sample organized in collaboration
with the havichivik community all hunters elders
artisans shamans and children are involved in
this ritual with a simple blow torch a meteorite
fragment is heated up above its cure point the
hot spell erases the stone's magnetic history
on an alchemical level or metaphorical
level the colonial weight is lifted
triggering triggering a new opening and now
we switch to louie yeah i actually i have the
the magnetometers that we've been building for the
last two years maybe it's also interesting to show
live so you saw in the photo um it's kind of like
this yellow box i don't know if you can see it
there yeah and what we do is we build the circuit
uh with a gps so which is really handy because
then we know where we're collecting the data and
at the same time we have this kind of customized
electronic circuit with a little screen a gps like
a micro controller and then connected to this box
we have yeah the geo tool and most of you probably
know the magnetometer from this like barrington
uh this kind of like little tube with like three
axis flux skates inside it's a similar thing to
that but we kind of customized the housing to
be completely different and then these are the
flux gate sensors and so what we do is when we're
in greenland we have i think three or four of
these devices um they're all 3d printed and then
we walk through the terrain with the intuit people
measuring the geomagnetic values of it so
and we do this for a few hours each day so
it's not like cyclic but it's just more
like momentary readings of the intensity
okay um yeah so we're on this
like final chapter right now
we believe that immersive methods of storytelling
evoke a deeper emotional response compared to
scientific visualizations of just pie charts
and data percentages in geomorphic video 2017
art theorist ursula biman calls for an urgency
of embodied interpretation of scientific data
she says quote it is fairly easy to access vast
amounts of scientific data about the climate and
environment but the explanation of data cannot
alone help us to understand the magnitude of the
change ahead of us aesthetics that are capable of
reaching the imaginary will be necessary and these
often call a fictional status so for us after
reading this quote we were really encouraged
by the words of byron for our kind of project out
of focus about this idea of material imaginaries
the step beyond scientific communication so
also finding ways to work with data and science
and these phenomenas of geomagnetism but in
more kind of artistic communication senses
so our custom magnetometer instruments convey
the landscapes expression beyond kind of the
binaries of zero and one through these combined
lenses of art and science the viewer can immerse
themselves in this kind of spectral polyphony
of disrupted geology and that's like the idea
of listening and being completely surrounded by
all these sounds of the landscape ice carving
thunders narwhal electro clicking frantic beluga
sopranos nomadic radio chatter helicopter blades
clapping and hunting boat rumbles tune the
listeners further into the accelerated geography
now we switch again
so um and some words about our
cinematic and artistic methods um
which align with bruno latour's criticism of
anthropogenic aesthetics so in the verifiable
image of the world 2019 he writes quote we are
so accustomed to seeing our blue planet from the
outside in as if we were imprisoned in a ruckus
space station or sitting on the throne of god
that we have completely forgotten to what
extent this astronomical image of the world
poorly reflects the common habitat shared by the
living unquote looking at the earth from above
creates this illusion of separation in which
the viewer seemingly does not participate in the
object of viewing that is the shifting landscape
this way of seeing certainly remains the deception
as humans are part of nature and earth is their
habitat surprisingly even when artistically
addressing the issues of the anthropocene many
methods and tools are identical to those used in
landscape extraction sorry drone filming satellite
mapping and remote sensing in this way the images
of ecological disasters fall into a category
of horrifying but sublime aesthetics examples
range from the epic drone shots of ice calving
to the captures of fluorescent toxic tailings
and admitting latorre's criticism of probing
the earth outside in our strategy is to trace
the evidence of shifting landscape from
the inside out through listening to the
sounds of fluctuating geomagnetic fields
the crew is guided across the terrain
in this way the sonic maps conduct a dramaturgy
of navigating in space composing the audiovisual
narrative this approach invites the landscape to
speak scream and stutter applying this perspective
of object-oriented ontology by looking through
the material lenses of the landscape the project
constructs a narrative that shifts away from the
colonial framing besides physical conquest uh
the danish and american colonists constructed
their own hierarchical interpretations of the
greenlandic landscape and culture and to bypass
these biased perspectives the fragments of kapiak
mitre become important non-human storytellers
and story triggers throughout the project
yeah so not only in our project we kind of
have these sound dialogues with the landscape
and objects and the meteorites but the artistic
materialities are always explored in relation
to the humans so to the people who actually
live there to ourselves also who come there um
so the project becomes also a platform that gives
voice to the inuit people who are directly bound
with the landscape um so our communication
with the local community was made possible
by the camac hunter and rock and roll musician
uh alakazak perry who when we actually went
to greenland we didn't have a translator and we
spent like i don't know three or four days making
quick posters and putting them on uh shops saying
hey we need a translator so that we can actually
also communicate with people who live there and
it turned out that alakazak perry who decided
to be our translator he was the great great grand
son of robert perry who was actually the american
explorer who went to the north pole and then
bought the cape york meteorite and a kitsok
back to new york in 1897. so that was like
also like a little side story there um
and this is him with his like rock and roll
band right near the top of greenland um
yeah so over the last seven months
the stories narrated by the people
of the great irons have been translated from in
luctan to english by miyuki dairana from kanek
and so the language is only speaking by less
than 900 people so it's been also a real mission
to find ways of translating this language
also into english because a lot of the words
have plural meanings and yeah miyuki theron has
been doing an amazing job with us and she has a
background in uh anthropology specializing in the
anthropocene also and this really contributes to
building a climate aware narrative from an inuit
position additionally the efforts to transcribe
and translate spoken accounts contribute also
to the preservation of the inductant language
which is vanishing and like i
said spoken by very few people
yeah and actually that's kind
of the end of our presentation
kind of but we thought it would be really
fun to play for everyone here a five-minute
audio recording which kind of narrates our own
experiences of being on this island for a month
and so the audio recording has sounds of let's
say it's not data solidification but it's
taking this magnetometer recordings and turning
it into sound there's field recordings in there
so it's a real journey of sound so if you have
headphones it'd be great if you plug headphones in
and i will just go ahead and play
the sounds so thank you for listening
okay
come on
foreign
so
oh
me
come on
be
oh
hey
yeah that was it so thank you excellent thank
you all very much thank you very much lewis
and susanna we can um give them both a a round
of applause there for a really interesting and
very different talk from our usual uh scientific
figure it's really good thank you so we have um
some time for for uh questions if anybody has
any questions uh to throw it lewis or zuzana
so i know we have one in the
chat which came early on from
uh from william harbour um he was asking are
you using esris or story maps in in your work
and will you create a sort of story map
version of the insights that you have had
uh story map yeah i mean at the end so
what we've actually just presented is pure
research and kind of more experiential like things
happening in the moment and so at the end i guess
it won't be a story map but it will be a film so
it will actually be a formal one hour documentary
slash art film science film um and we'll be
distributing that also so we'll invite everyone to
come and watch that film when it's finished and
we can't say when it will be finished because
we've also decided to go back to greenland this
summer and spend more time there making recordings
listening to sounds and just being there in
the landscape that's really important for us so
we'll let you know when the film is released and
everyone can come and see it back in the cinemas
that would be really good
um does anybody else have
any questions i've got a bundle um but i
don't want to i don't want to take over
i have a question as well yeah that's so cool um
really different from what we see normally but
it's so awesome it's the first time i listened
to paleomagnetic data i think so i was wondering
because your your sound thing was multiple sounds
over each other and i was wondering which one were
like the the recordings from the geomagnetic field
was that like the bass sounds or yeah and also
this other stuff yeah and uh yeah some we also
picked up some um we we believe to be a morse code
from american um air base which is uh yeah the
closest settlement to the yeah to the settlement
we were um we were at um and besides that yeah
indeed it's um a lot of filled field recordings um
with the use of also hydrophone and other
microphones so um yeah so these all these
layers are combined into one so to say soundscape
and i also wanted to add that um some sounds
were made by the hunters who were using our
geotools and also exploring the landscape so
yeah we wanted to kind of collaborate with them
and not to perhaps only document their life
uh so so we we also really believe that they
are part of uh the authors of the project in
in some way yeah yeah so also the it's maybe
we didn't cover it also and the sounds is the
flux gate magnetometer which we kind of
built ourselves that's translating the
fluctuations i guess with a really high sample
rate so it's very fast reading and then we also
we have a basically in the landscape
we have a big dipole antenna which is
like two probes of aluminium that go into
the permafrost and it's i think it's cool
someone can correct me actually probably there's
magnetolyric measuring um so we have this giant
dipole on the ground and that's when i think
we picked up all these kind of natural radio
signals the military base all this other stuff
because of the noise um but so we're trying all
these different kind of scientific techniques
also in the kind of idea of listening purely
well thanks very much um i mean i guess if nobody
else has got a question my my question really
is um what inspired you to to look at um the
magnetic fields and and the magnetization the
memory in rocks i mean what was the kind
of spark that set you off down this road
yeah actually we made a film uh before uh which
was looking at a very specific case study which
was the port of rotterdam and we were really
interested in the port of rotterdam because
we'd heard that the port of rotterdam had
become this local magnetic anomaly and the
reason for that was the fact that um giant iron
ore mines in baffin island canada and in brazil
had been digging up all the raw material
and then dumping it in the port of rotterdam
to then later on be turned into steel in germany
and by putting this huge island of iron ore in
the middle of the port of rotterdam had created
this kind of local anomaly so we were really
interested in trying to make a project about this
kind of invisible phenomena and how we've also
come from a design practice so we're also really
interested in how things can be communicated uh
we're interested in language we're interested in
this kind of variety of things so we were always
fascinated with how can you communicate invisible
phenomena it's like almost the biggest challenge
so that i mean that's also the exciting
thing and for us it's also a lot down to
interpretation things that are uh anomalies
that's also an attraction uh so yeah that's
kind of for us i guess maybe you can add something
to them yeah that's that's actually what i wanted
to say so we come from visual communication
kind of background and yeah primarily we were
quite concerned with images only and then i
think um yeah i mean everything is waves so
then it expands into uh this quest of trying to
understand how to map other waves and how can we
um yeah how can we reach uh understanding of them
and uh what does it give to us what kind of data
it can or like what kind of information is hidden
in that so uh yeah also hence that the interest in
climate change and um mineral extraction and how
um that affects also people um yeah and for us
also this aspect of uh indigenous cosmology this
that um sees the the cosmos in quite similar
way um as we see geomagnetism nowadays so um
this world woven out of uh invisible waves and
also i mean yeah high arctic is uh uh completely
dark half of the year so i think these imaginaries
of what we can't see become very prominent so yeah
we kind of became fascinated by all these aspects
together i think and um yeah combining them
but then also being open for serendipity uh going
to greenland because uh some things we could not
foresee and were quite surprising to
us so yeah that's just the way we work
yeah all right so thanks very much
um i think we've got time for one uh one
other quick question if anybody has has one
no well okay i'll have one very quick well
hopefully very quickly and you know when you're
actually doing the readings with the magnetometer
and you said you sort of walked around some areas
where you know were you just focused around
just local villages that you were at or did you
actually go you know walk around further afield
sort of thing yeah that's a good question um so we
had like a base camp i guess where we would leave
the magnetometer for like a 24-hour cycle so you'd
have that kind of longevity of a kind of baseline
data and i think that was something like 58
000 nano teslas we were getting from this
kind of like baseline data and then what we
wanted to do is yeah like we said before we
really love anomalies that's for us is the
interesting thing so we had this kind of
theory that potentially meteorite craters
where the meteorite had fallen maybe it left some
remnant magnetism or maybe there were other things
happening there or how could we also look for
geological features like a magnetite outcrop of
geology would that also be a kind of anomaly in
relation to the base level so we put all these
devices in movement to kind of explore the terrain
by trying to listen for these anomalies basically
so that's when you hear the sound going like going
crazy that's the anomaly because the flux gate
just can't handle that kind of high field yeah
so it was really an exploration and i think that
was really beautiful for the project is we didn't
have like a map or coordinates like we'd go out on
these hunting boats and just try and like guide
ourselves through geomagnetism fields basically
cool excellent thank you very much um i
think we can give um lewis and zuzan another
round of applause for a really a
different really quite interesting
uh talk thank you guys it was really good um so
just before we wrap up um for um for the evening
well just for some background noise here and just
a a quick reminder um of uh some of our upcoming
uh seminars we've got two more seminars um in may
in a couple weeks time in a month's time and then
we have a short break um over the egu uh week and
then we will come back um to a slightly different
time slot so we'll switch to a european eastern
hemisphere time slot so our seminars will move to
uh a morning time slot uh in in the european uh
hemisphere um and as always we are uh looking for
uh more speakers so if anybody is interested
in giving a scientific talk an artistic talk
or any kind of talk that is um magnetic in any
way um please reach out to us and let us know and
we can we can arrange you into our schedule and
lastly just a quick reminder that today's seminar
and of the previous seminars that we've had um
are will be available on on our youtube channel
so if you missed out on anything today or
anything in the past please look us up on on
youtube to to catch up so thank you everyone for
joining this week's magnets and i look forward to
seeing you all in a couple of weeks time thank
you all very much cheers thank you thank you